<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nevves of the complement of the art of nauigation And of the mightie empire of Cataia. Together with the Straits of Anian. By A.L. The principall contents whereof follow in the next page.</title>
            <author>Linton, Anthony.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05570</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15692</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109469</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845116</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845116</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9997</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05570)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9997)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 721:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nevves of the complement of the art of nauigation And of the mightie empire of Cataia. Together with the Straits of Anian. By A.L. The principall contents whereof follow in the next page.</title>
                  <author>Linton, Anthony.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 44, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The author's name, Anthony Linton, appears on A2 recto.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Navigation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Nautical astronomy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9997:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9997:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>NEWES OF THE COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PLEMENT OF THE ART OF NAVIGATION. AND OF THE MIGHTIE Empire of <hi>Cataia.</hi> TOGETHER WITH THE Straits of <hi>Anian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By A. L.</p>
            <p>The principall Contents whereof fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>in the next page.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device belonging to Thomas Orton (?)</figDesc>
               <q>BY PEACE PLENTI. BY WISDOME PEACE</q>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:9997:2"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> THe excellencie of Nauigation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> The imperfectnes of the Arte of Nauigation, as it now ſtandeth.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> The meanes of perfecting the ſame.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> The benefits of the ſame ſo perfected.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> Of the mightie Empire of Cataia, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> The tender of theſe my preſent Newes: vnto &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> Of finding the longitudes by celestial obſeruation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the helpe of any Ecclipſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8</hi> The concluſion.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:9997:2"/>
            <head>TO ALL AND SINGVLER THE SVB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>IECTS OF THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, IAMES by the grace of God, King of Great <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> defender of the Faith, &amp;c. being <hi>Mathematicians, Merchants, Nauigators, Trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers,</hi> &amp;c. And alſo to all other, furtherers and fauourers of <hi>Geographie, Nauigation,</hi> and <hi>Diſcoueries;</hi> and to euerie of them, reſpectiuely; ANTHONIE LYNTON <hi>Parſon of</hi> Worth, <hi>in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of</hi> Suſſex, <hi>wiſheth health, and all true happineſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL dutiful offices vnto you, and euery one of you, with due reſpect, and faſhion an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable, premiſed and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, &amp;c. When I conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, with what great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment you reade the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of <hi>Iapon,</hi> and <hi>China,</hi> contained in the yearly letters and miſſiues of the Ieſuite Friers, (folke of other nations, and inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting in remote countries, and of a ſect corrupt in religion, which produceth, as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:9997:3"/>ſpeaketh, Pſal. 144.12. <hi>Strange children, whoſe mouth talketh of vanitie, and their right hand is a right hand of iniquitie:</hi> as well witneſſeth our owne late feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full experience in their powder treaſon, and the ruine of many noble Perſonages, and families, in this weſterne world, by their meanes.) It gaue me occaſion to aſſure my ſelfe, that you will with no leſſe content, reade, and conſider alſo theſe newes, written by an Engliſh man borne, a Miniſter of the Goſpell, and dwelling amongſt you: Newes, I ſay, of things verie ſtrange, pleaſant and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, both to your priuate ſelues, and alſo to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like State; and ſuch as many yeeres paſt haue been greatly deſired, &amp; yet neuer vnto this day knowne, nor ſcant hoped for: comprized in two principall heads. The former whereof is of the complement of the Art of Nauigation. The other is of the great and mightie Empire of <hi>Cataia,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label>1</label> Nauigation (as you know better then I can report) is an art more excellent and eminent, then any other of the like kind in vſe and practiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs; whether you conſider the dignitie, the neceſſitie, or the vtilitie thereof.</p>
            <p>The dignitie of Nauigation will moſt euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare, if you conſider from whence it taketh his originall, namely, from Arithmetique, Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrie, &amp; Aſtronomie, the three moſt glorious of the ſeuen Liberall Sciences, which three ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and truly were called <hi>Acröamatica,</hi> and were the ſtudies of Kings &amp; greateſt Princes. All which ſaid three Liberall Sciences muſt neceſſarily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre, both in the making vp, &amp; alſo in the practiſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:9997:3"/>of Nauigation, ſo as no one of them can bee miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in any caſe: which happeneth in no other practique ſcience or diſcipline whatſoeuer in vſe amongſt vs; and therefore Nauigation (as a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Queene, attended vpon by many honorable Ladies) is of great dignitie, as wel for the ofſpring, as alſo for the practiſe of the ſame.</p>
            <p>The neceſſitie thereof is moſt apparent: for without it the nations of the world dwelling farre aſunder, neither ſhould nor could euer at any hand by traffique or commerce be partakers of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers commodities, manners, learning, policies or religion; without which how miſerable mankind ſhould be, or haue been, your wiſdomes can eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie conceiue, and ſpecially the <hi>Inſulani,</hi> which without this Art ſhould dwell alone ſauage, and barbarous, and in great want of things needfull both for their bodies and ſoules, and ſhould alſo want all means to vent their owne excellent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, to the vſe &amp; benefit of others. Nay ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny goodly and great Ilands of the world as well as ſmall, ſhould not to this day haue been repleniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with people, but haue remained void and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate, as doe <hi>S. Hellens,</hi> and the Hollanders, <hi>Mauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius,</hi> and others and mankind thereby haue been diminiſhed; and Gods glorie left without witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in thoſe places.</p>
            <p>Nauigation doth likewiſe liuely ſhew it ſelfe vnto the leaſt view or conſideration of the wiſe, to be a ſcience and practiſe of ſingular profit: ſeeing that without it the life of man can hardly be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued. For there is no Countrie, no Prouince, no
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:9997:4"/>Citie euerie way ſufficient, well to ſuſtaine it ſelfe, but euery one of them hath need of others helpe and ſuccour. All which for the moſt part be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied by Nauigation, and without it, cannot well and commodiouſly be had. Yea, and the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher is of mind: That it behooueth cities and kingdomes to haue ſhipping in ſtore, and in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe for Nauigation, if they meane to enioy their liberties, and to rule ouer others. For clearing of all which, let theſe few examples heere recited, ſerue in the ſtead of many arguments.</p>
            <p>Of the Kingdome of <hi>Iſrael</hi> vnder <hi>Salomon,</hi> it is thus written, 1. King. 10.22. For the King had on the ſea a Nauie of <hi>Tharſis,</hi> with the Nauie of <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram:</hi> once in three yeeres came the Nauie of <hi>Tharſis,</hi> and brought gold and ſiluer, and Iuorie, and Apes, and Peacocks.</p>
            <p>It ſeemeth that this Nauie of <hi>Tharſis</hi> (of great ſhips for the ſea, as one interpreteth it) was only for the trade to the Iſles of <hi>Cittim,</hi> in the <hi>Pelopone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> ſea, and other townes vpon the coaſts and Ilands of the <hi>Mare Mediterraneum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For of the ſhippes of the red ſea; that went to <hi>Ophir</hi> for gold, the Scripture ſpeaketh otherwiſe, 1. King. 9.26. <hi>viz.</hi> Alſo King <hi>Salomon</hi> made a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie of ſhips in <hi>Aſiongabar,</hi> which is beſides <hi>Elot,</hi> and the brinck of the red ſea in the land of <hi>Edom.</hi> 27. And <hi>Hyram</hi> ſent with the Nauie his ſeruants that were mariners, and had knowledge of the ſea, with the ſeruants of <hi>Salomon.</hi> 28. And they came to <hi>Ophir,</hi> and ſet from thence foure hundred and twentie Talents of gold, and brought it to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:9997:4"/>King <hi>Salomon.</hi> The effect of theſe Nauies you may reade, 1. King. 10.23. And ſo King <hi>Salomon</hi> excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all the Kings of the earth, both in riches and wiſdome. verſ. 26. Then <hi>Salomon</hi> gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chariots and horſe-men: and he had a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand and foure hundred chariots, &amp; twelue thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand horſe-men, whom he placed in the Chariot-cities, and with the King at <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> verſ. 27. And the King gaue ſiluer in <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> as ſtones, &amp; gaue Cedars as the wild fig-trees, which grow abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly vpon the plaine, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tyrus</hi> alſo flouriſhed exceedingly by Nauigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: it is euident in that the prophane Authors do attribute the inuention of ſhips and ſayling vnto that nation, I meane the <hi>Phoenicians,</hi> citizens of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> and other ſea townes adioyning thereunto, as witneſſeth <hi>Tibullus, Eleg.</hi> 7. as he is cited by <hi>Polydor Virgil, Dererum inuent. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 15.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Vt maris vastum proſpectet turribus Aequor.</l>
               <l>Prima ratem ventis credere docta Tyros.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The holy Scriptures alſo are euident records hereof. <hi>Eſay</hi> the Prophet ſpeaketh thus, chap. 22.8. Who hath decreed this againſt <hi>Tyrus</hi> (that crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth men) whoſe merchants are Princes, whoſe chapmen are the Nobles of the world. And <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel</hi> chap. 27.3. declareth the glorious eſtate ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And verſ. 25. The ſhippes of <hi>Tharſis</hi> were the chiefe in thy Merchandize, and thou waſt reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and made verie glorious in the middeſt of the ſea. verſ. 27. Thy riches, thy faires, thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, thy Mariners and Pilots, thy Calkers, and the occupiers of thy Merchandize, and all the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:9997:5"/>men of warre that are in thee, ſhall fall in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the ſea, in the day of thy ruine.</p>
            <p>Call to remembrance that old <hi>Carthage</hi> alſo, a renowmed ofſpring of <hi>Tyrus,</hi> which only by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uigation and trading by ſea, grew ſo mightie, that three ſeuerall times it tooke occaſion to ſtand out with Rome for the Soueraigntie, in three ſeuerall warres, great, doubtfull, and lamentable. In the firſt of which, it is reported, that the Carthagine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were beaten in a battel at the ſea, &amp; ſo brought in order. In the ſecond warre, which happened ſome fortie yeeres after, they were growne againe ſo ſtrong, that beſides many battels by land, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in <hi>Italie</hi> fifteene yeares together, they fought with the Romans a great battell by ſea; in which likewiſe they had the worſt, as witneſſeth <hi>Tit. Liu. Dec.</hi> 3. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. and at length being enforced by the Romans to yeeld, their citie had been vtterly ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the ground, had they not redeemed the ſame with teares, and a yeerelie tribute of two hundred <hi>Euboian</hi> talents; and withall concluded with the Romans, neuer after to haue and keepe moe ſhips for warre, then ten, &amp;c. as writeth <hi>Appi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in <hi>Lybico.</hi> Yet neuertheleſſe the Carthagineans, within fiftie yeeres after that, grew againe ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding mightie by ſea and land, that they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke a third warre againſt the Romans, in which they were ouercome by ſea and by land, and their noble Citie, which had ſtood ſeuen hundred yeares in great eſtate, was raced vnto the ground: (ſo that Nauigation which was at the firſt the cauſe of their greatnes, was alſo at the laſt the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:9997:5"/>of their ruine, being ouermaſtred by the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans in ſtrength at ſea, as well witneſſe the ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>Hanno,</hi> and <hi>Cato Cenſorinus, in Appion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae bello Lybico;</hi> whereby may be ſeene the great vtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Nauigation.</p>
            <p>Conſider alſo the Cities of <hi>Greece,</hi> as <hi>Athens, Corinth,</hi> and the reſidue vpon the ſea coaſt; yea, and the very ſmall Iſlands of the <hi>Aegëan</hi> ſea; as <hi>Samos</hi> and ſuch like: how much they encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in renowne and riches by their ſhipping and Nauigation, and the vtilitie thereof will plainelie appeare. That I ſay nothing of the Greeke and Roman Empires, in whom their <hi>Naualia</hi> are not the leaſt memorable in ancient ſtories.</p>
            <p>Neither may I here forget the ſea forces, and ſea ſeruices of the now floriſhing and menacing Empire of the Turks, which are not vnknowne to the world: Reade M. <hi>Hakluyte</hi> (who hath excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentlie well deſerued of our whole Nation, in his worthie works of our Engliſh Voiages.) vol. 2. part. 2. pag. 78. where you ſhall find ſpecified 268. veſſels for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> war that beſieged the <hi>Rhodes:</hi> beſides the Nauie that lay attending in other places to cut off al ſuccours of Chriſtians, &amp;c. and elſewhere in thoſe his volumes.</p>
            <p>Conſider further the Venetians, and the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowaies, how by Nauigation they haue ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and increaſed their great Eſtates.</p>
            <p>Then turne your eies vpon <hi>Spaine, Portugall,</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> now of late yeeres, how as they haue been better furniſhed with ſhipping, ſo haue they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:9997:6"/>had their riches, honours, and Eſtates increaſed euen to wonderment.</p>
            <p>Looke ouer the world, vnto the great Empire of <hi>China,</hi> which at this preſent doth abound with ſhipping, both for the Inland ſeas and riuers, to trade at home amongſt themſelues with eaſineſſe and ſpeede; and alſo for the vaſte Ocean, for tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with forraine nations; whereby infinite numbers of that people are ſet a worke, and their riches and renowne is growne vnto the world, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie admirable, as witneſſeth Maſter <hi>Hackluit</hi> in his workes of our Engliſh Voiages, vol. 2. par. 2. pag. 77. 92. and vol. 3. pag. 837. 858. Reade al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>Arthus de India orientali.</hi> pag. 466. 468. Alſo reade <hi>Pantogia.</hi> pag. 56. 61. 64. 65. 112. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, let vs returne home vnto our owne Countrie, this Realme of England, and we ſhall find the eſtate thereof much encreaſed, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by Nauigation. By Nauigation we reade that <hi>Edgar,</hi> (that I may vſe his owne words in his ſtile) <hi>Anglorum Baſileus, omniumque Regum, Inſula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, Oceanique Britannia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> circumiacentis; cunctarum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que nationum, quae infra eam includuntur, Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, &amp; Dominus;</hi> who raigned <hi>anno dom.</hi> 959. kept his ſeas from Piracy, and his land from for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine inuaſions. For euery yeere he rigged 4000. ſaile of ſhippes, and diuiding them into foure companies, put them to ſea, vpon the foure quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of his kingdome, for the ſame purpoſe. By Nauigation, our Armies haue been tranſported into other lands for ſeruice there: So <hi>Iohn</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> with a Nauie of 500. ſhips, tranſported
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:9997:6"/>his Armie into <hi>Ireland, ann</hi> 1206. So our Armie and forces were tranſported by Sir <hi>Francis Drake</hi> Knight, vnto S. <hi>Domingo,</hi> and <hi>Carthagena,</hi> in the Weſt <hi>Indies, anno</hi> 1585. and into <hi>Portugale, anno</hi> 1589. By Nauigation many ſtrong battels haue been fought at ſea by our nation, and honorable victories obtained: as the battell at <hi>Sluce,</hi> by King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, <hi>anno</hi> 1340. the <hi>French</hi> Fleet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of 400. ſaile. As alſo the battell fought at <hi>Hareflew</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> by King <hi>Henrie</hi> the fifth, againſt the <hi>French</hi> Nauie of 500. ſhips, <hi>anno</hi> 1414. As was alſo that moſt renowmed victorie gotten, from and of that vaunted inuincible <hi>Spaniſh Armada, anno</hi> 1588. And that ouer the Nauie Royall of the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> gotten in the Bay of <hi>Cadiz, anno.</hi> 1596. By Nauigation, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleet, that came to waft ouer King <hi>Philip</hi> from <hi>Douer</hi> into the <hi>Low-countries, anno</hi> 1556. was compelled by a few ſhips of the Nauie Royall of this Land, vnder the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of the Right Honorable, the Lord <hi>William Howard,</hi> Baron of <hi>Effingham,</hi> then Lord high Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall of <hi>England,</hi> (and father to the now Right Honorable, and renowmed Lord <hi>Charles Howard,</hi> Earle of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> and Lord high Admirall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of <hi>England,</hi>) to ſtrike their ſailes, and vaile their bonnets, and performe ſuch honorable acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgements, as were done at ſea, to the Emperiall Crowne of this Land. The like alſo was done by ten ſhips of the Nauie Royall of our late Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of famous memorie, vnder the conduct of the aforeſaid <hi>Charles Howard,</hi> now the Right Honorable Earle of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> Lord high Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:9997:7"/>of <hi>England,</hi> vnto the great <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleet of 130. ſhips, conducting the Emperours Siſter, the ſpouſe of <hi>Spaine,</hi> thorow the narrow Seas, into <hi>Spaine;</hi> vnder whoſe worthie, and happie conduct alſo, the two honorable victories ouer the <hi>Spaniſh Armadaes,</hi> laſt before mentioned, were obtained, to his immortall fame and glorie. By Nauigation, the Northerne ſeas vnto <hi>Ruſland,</hi> and <hi>Moſcouia,</hi> were happily diſcouered, <hi>anno</hi> 1553. and a happie trade of Merchandize opened thither, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth vnto this day. By Nauigation, the Eaſt and Weſt <hi>Indies</hi> haue bin ſailed vnto, by our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> nation; the bottome of the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> ſeas ſearched, and the great Emperour of the <hi>Turkes</hi> at his <hi>Seragno,</hi> or Port in <hi>Constantinople,</hi> Royally ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, to his great content; ſince which time, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he, nor his Succeſſors, haue been ſo forward as before, to make warre vpon the Chriſtians: Yea and by Nauigation, the huge conuexitie of the whole world, within little more then theſe 30. yeares laſt paſt, hath been by our <hi>Engliſh</hi> nation twice ſailed about. Once, by the worthie Sir <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Drake</hi> Knight, and the ſecond time, by the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie <hi>Thomas Candiſh</hi> Eſquire, both paſſing tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the Straits of <hi>Magellan,</hi> into the South ſea, and ſo coaſting from thence the Weſterne ſhore of the New world, vnto <hi>California,</hi> paſſed from thence vnto the <hi>Moluccan</hi> Ilands, and from thence by <hi>Iaua,</hi> and by the Cape, <hi>De bona Eſperanza,</hi> and returned againe aliue into this Realme of <hi>England,</hi> with riches and renowne. A voyage neuer yet before this day performed (for any thing I know
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:9997:7"/>to the contrarie) by any other, of what nation ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, but only by <hi>Magellan</hi> the <hi>Portugale,</hi> who firſt found his ſo called Straits; <hi>anno</hi> 1520. as <hi>Arthus</hi> reporteth, pag. 411. but periſhed himſelfe before he returned againe into <hi>Spaine.</hi> So that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer may be ſaid of the increaſe of our wealth, and riches, I cannot tell, but this I am ſure of, that our Eſtate (through the goodneſſe and protection of the Almightie, to whom be all praiſe and honor for the ſame for euermore,) hath been mightily defended, and ſecured by our Nauigation, in ſuch ſort, that as in former times, ſo now at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent day, our glorie and honor ſhineth with great brightnes, in the middeſt of the mightie Empires, and great Kingdomes of <hi>Europe.</hi> Neither haue the ancient Kings of this Land neglected the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement thereof. But as in ancient times, the Kings of the <hi>Latins</hi> ſtamped a ſhip vpon their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, in remembrance of the great benefits that their Land had receiued of <hi>Saturnus,</hi> which from the ſea had arriued amongſt them, as witneſſeth <hi>Ouid, Fast. lib.</hi> 1. in theſe words:</p>
            <q>
               <l>At bona posteritas puppim formauit in aere,</l>
               <l>Hoſpitis aduentum testificata Dei.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Euen ſo, the ancient renowmed Kings of this Land, coyned their gold, on the one ſide with a ſhip vpon the ſea, teſtifying thereby, the great commodities that came vnto their Land by Naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</p>
            <p>All which examples rightly and duely conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, do liuely manifeſt the great vtilitie of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uigation.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:9997:8"/>
            <p>So that we may conclude, that Nauigation is the moſt excellent Art of all others of like pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, both for the dignitie, neceſſitie, and vtilitie thereof.</p>
            <p>And yet neuertheleſſe this moſt excellent Art, by which ſo much good commeth, and ſo many excellent and memorable things haue been, and are daily performed, is yet very imperfect, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpon no warrantable and ſufficient grounds and rules whereby it may be dulie practiſed. As witneſſeth Sir <hi>Humfrey Gilbert</hi> Knight, who ſaith of himſelfe in theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi> I haue deuiſed to amend the errors of vſuall ſea Chards, whoſe common fault is to make the degrees of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in euery Latitude of one like bigneſſe. And haue alſo deuiſed therein a ſphericall Inſtrument, with a Compaſſe of variation, for the perfect knowing of the Longitude. And a preciſe order to pricke the ſea Chard, &amp;c. <hi>Engl. voiag. vol.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 24.</p>
            <p>And M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Thomas Digges,</hi> that excellent <hi>Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matician,</hi> in his Preface to the Reader, of his <hi>Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiaticos,</hi> hath theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt therefore, by Demonſtrations Mathematicall, finding the great imperfections in the Art of Nauigation, &amp; groſſe errors practiſed by the Maſters and Mariners of this our age: I ſought by reaſon to perſwade with ſome of them, to alter and reforme their Chards, Inſtruments, and erroneous Rules, ſhewing them infallible Demonſtrations of their errors. And a little after: By proofe I found, and thoſe maſters themſelues could not but confeſſe, that experience
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:9997:8"/>did no leſſe plainly diſcouer the errors of their Rules, then my Demonſtrations.</p>
            <p>And M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>William Burrowes,</hi> ſometime Control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the Royall Nauie, of our late Queene <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> of famous memorie, in his Epiſtle wherein his Mappe of <hi>Ruſsia</hi> was to her dedicated, hath theſe words; <hi>viz.</hi> It is ſo, that there are Rules vſed in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uigation, which are not perfectly true, amongſt which, the ſtraight lines in the ſea Chards repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting two and thirtie points of the Compaſſe or winds, are not holden to be the leaſt: &amp;c. but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of ſuch talkers for principall, to condemne the occupiers thereof for ignorant, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Richard Polter,</hi> one of the late foure principall maſters of his Maieſties Nauie Royall, in his booke called the path-way to perfect ſailing, printed at <hi>London, anno</hi> 1605. deliuereth a great number of abſurdities, in the ſaid Art of Nauiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Edward Wright,</hi> a verie learned Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematician, hath (not long ſince) publiſhed a booke likewiſe of the errors in the Art of Naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation; which booke I haue ſeene, but neuer read the ſame, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>So that this noble Art of Nauigation, although it be ſo excellent, is yet neuertheleſſe imperfect, and founded vpon no ſufficient Rules of Art, whereby it may be generally practiſed as it ought.</p>
            <p>And although it may be obiected, that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sir <hi>Humfrey Gilbert,</hi> and <hi>Richard Polter,</hi> &amp; other, haue attempted the reformations of theſe imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, but alſo that M. <hi>Edw. Wright</hi> hath lately
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:9997:9"/>perfected the ſame, ſo that all errors and abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are by him reformed. I anſwere &amp; freely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that the ſaid M. <hi>Wright</hi> hath exceedingly wel deſerued of Nauigation, and ſpecially in that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection of the ſea Mappe by him deuiſed, (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to which, the Mappe commonly annexed to the volumes of our Engliſh Diſcoueries, and the great quarter Maps publiſhed at <hi>Amsterdam</hi> by <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docus Hondius, anno</hi> 1602. are framed): but yet I am aſſured, that his reformation will be found to fall far ſhort of perfection, when his trauels ſhall come to ſtrict examination, not becauſe he wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth either learning, or diligence therein, but a good foundation whereon to raiſe his worke, that is, the knowledge of the magnetical poles hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mentioned: ſo that the ſaid Art, although it be by his induſtrie and trauels very much amended, yet is it far from being perfected.</p>
            <p>This excellent and profitable Art of Nauigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (but very vnperfect, for any thing that is yet publikely knowne to the contrarie) I preſume I haue by the great bleſſing of Almightie God in Chriſt Ieſus our Sauiour, not without exceeding paines and labours in and about the ſame, brought to very good perfection, and furniſhed it with all the Complements therof, and am able at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, by his grace, to enforme any of you (of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent knowledge and capacity for the ſame) how he may practiſe the ſame, with as great facility, and expedition, as now is done, and with ſo great cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie make his concluſions, of Latitude, Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and variation, as is poſſible to be done in any
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:9997:9"/>other Mathematicall practiſe, in vſe amongſt vs, depending vpon continued obſeruation. And this is the firſt end and maine purpoſe of all my labours taken in and about my mentioned Complement.</p>
            <p>And for as much, as many learned men here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, haue profeſſed thus much, with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things touching this Art, all which for the moſt part, are vaniſhed away like ſmoke, and quite gone as though they had neuer been: by reaſon whereof, you may eaſily be induced, to hope for no better ſucceſſe at my hands, of theſe my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Complements. I haue therefore thought good, for your better ſatisfaction and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to ſet downe in order, ſome few of the chiefeſt heads in theſe my trauels, propoſed and concluded, together with ſome Corrolaries from them deduced, as followeth, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That (although a great learned man and his followers, abſolutely denie that there is any fixed pole magneticall, yet neuer theleſſe) there are two fixed poles magneticall, which are the maine grounds of the Art of Nauigation, and without which the ſaid Art cannot be well and ſufficiently practiſed: the one Arctique, becauſe it is within the Arctique circle, the other Antarctique, for the like reaſon; much different from the poles of the world, and alſo from all and euerie the fancied magneticall poles heretofore publiſhed.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That theſe magnetical poles are vpon the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies of the Globe of the earth, and haue a magne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:9997:10"/>axis, paſſing betweene them thorow the Centre of the ſaid earth.</p>
            <p n="3">3 What is the Longitude of either of the ſaid magneticall poles, from the ancient firſt meridian of the world, paſſing by the <hi>Canarie</hi> Ilands, or the meridian of any other place, whoſe Longitude from the ſaid firſt meridian is knowne. And alſo what Latitude either of the ſaid magneticall poles hath from the Equinoctiall.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That vpon theſe poles magnetical, as vpon their Centres, are to be conceiued and deſcribed (for the Art of Nauigation) vpon the ſuperficies of the Globe of the earth, an <hi>Aequator,</hi> parallels, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridians magneticall, much differing from thoſe of the world.</p>
            <p n="5">5 That there is one common meridian or great circle, paſſing thorow both the poles magneticall, and poles of the world, diuiding the ſuperficies of the earth, into two ſeuerall Hemiſpheres.</p>
            <p n="6">6 That in this common meridian, is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Longitude, to be accounted in the Art of Nauigation.</p>
            <p n="7">7 What is the difference of Longitude of this ſaid common meridian, either Eaſtwards, or Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards from the meridian of the <hi>Canaries,</hi> or from any other place, whoſe longitude from the ſaid Ilands is knowne.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:9997:10"/>
            <p n="8">8 That the North and South of the Compaſſe varie for the moſt part from the North and South of the world, the greateſt variation being of 180. degrees, which leſſeneth vntill it come to nothing.</p>
            <p n="9">9 That in euery parallel of the world, and in equal ſpaces in euery of them, this variation altereth, in ſome places encreaſing, in ſome places decreaſing, and in ſome places directing in ſelfe to the pole of the world; In ſome places of equall ſpace, it alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſwifter, and in ſome places it altereth ſlower; in ſome places it varieth to the Eaſtwards, and in ſome places to the Weſtwards, as is alreadie well knowne. And now all theſe places are giuen and knowne, where they be in euerie of the ſaid paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lels, and alſo the cauſes thereof.</p>
            <p n="10">10 That in euery parallel of the world, betweene the Equinoctiall and the poles magneticall, as alſo in the ſaid Equinoctiall, there be many ſeuerall places wherein the Compaſſe hath equall varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p n="11">11 That the ſaid places of equal variation in euery of the ſaid parallels, be not equally diſtant from the common meridian, but vnequally; and the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of this ſaid inequalite, is more, or leſſe, in different parallels.</p>
            <p n="12">12 That the longitude of all and euery the ſaid pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of equall variation, may eaſily be found out,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:9997:11"/>and deſcribed vpon the Globe and Chard with helique or tortuous lines, ſome of them tending from the Arctique pole of the world, vnto the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarctique pole magnetical: and contrariwiſe, ſome of them tending from the Antarctique pole of the world, to the Arctique pole magneticall, croſſing as well the Equinoctiall and Equator magneticall, as alſo almoſt all the parallels of both kinds.</p>
            <p n="13">13 That all the Rumbs deſcribed or ſuppoſed to be deſcribed by a ſhip ſailing vpon the ſea, except the meridians and parallels, be ſpirall lines, paſſing from the equinoctiall to the poles magnetical, and not to the poles of the world, as hath been hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to falſely ſuppoſed.</p>
            <p n="14">14 That all the ſaid ſpirall lines or Rumbs may be deſcribed vpon the Globe for Nauigation, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vpon the ſea Chards in <hi>plano,</hi> as well thoſe after M. <hi>Edw. Wright</hi> his proiection, as vpon others of two other proiections, not heretofore vſed in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uigation, yet beautifull to the eye, and conuenient for the practiſe of the ſaid Art of Nauigation.</p>
            <p n="15">15 That the Globes, and one ſort of ſea Chards may be made, without any Rumbs deſcribed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and yet ſerue as well and as readilie to all purpoſes for the vſe of Nauigatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as thoſe Globes and Chards may do, that haue the Rumbs or ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling lines deſcribed vpon them.</p>
            <p n="16">16 That the Globes and Chards thus deſcribed, do
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:9997:11"/>giue the longitudes and differences of longitudes of and betweene verie many places, and alſo the trendings of diuers coaſts ſomewhat otherwiſe then the ordinarie Globes and Mappes doe offer them; yet neuertheleſſe trulie and as they bee indeed.</p>
            <p n="17">17 Theſe Globes and Chards thus deſcribed; to find out by obſeruation, as well at ſea as at land, the magnitude of the variation of the Compaſſe for the place where ſuch obſeruation ſhall bee made, readily, and iuſtly, the Latitude of the place being firſt knowne, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="18">18 The variation of the Compaſſe and the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the place being giuen, to find out by Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meticall calculation the true Longitude of the ſame place.</p>
            <p n="19">19 Contrariwiſe the Latitude and Longitude of any place being giuen, to find out thereby the true variation in or at that place, and that alſo by Arithmeticall calculation.</p>
            <p n="20">20 Foure diuers other waies and meanes to find out at all times the Longitude of the place where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you make obſeruation, (or to pricke the Chard as it is commonly called) with as much eaſe and expedition, and with farre more certentie then now is or can be vſed in our moderne Nauigatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p n="21">21 A fift way, the height of the pole of the world
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:9997:12"/>being giuen, &amp;c. to find out at all times the Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude moſt certenlie without any regard had to the Rumbe wherein you haue ſailed, or the number of leagues you haue run, or the variation of the Compaſſe: by Arithmeticall calculation.</p>
            <p n="22">22 A ſixt way, the height of the pole being giuen, &amp;c. without any regard of the things laſt before mentioned, to performe the ſame by mechanicall practiſe ſpeedily.</p>
            <p>But here it is to be vnderſtood, that as euery one of theſe ſeuerall waies before mentioned of fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Longitude is warrantablie true, if the things required in them (<hi>vz.</hi> variations and eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and other things to be found by obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) be true; ſo likewiſe if the ſaid things required, be faultie; that then the longitudes alſo from them deriued will bee anſwerablie faultie in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, that ſeeing Nauigation ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth wholly vpon obſeruation, and all obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the ſame at ſea, be made by very ſmall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, as namely the ſailing Compaſſe, Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labe, and ſuch like, ſo that the variations and eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and ſuch like, found by ſuch obſeruations, be ſeldome true; and that therefore true longitudes are ſeldome to be found; yet neuertheleſſe how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it fall out it is certaine.</p>
            <p n="23">23 That by theſe ſeuerall waies aſſiſting each other in the hand of a Nauigator, the longitudes may be found ſufficiently true for the preciſe practiſe of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:9997:12"/>Nauigation, according as I haue propoſed. And becauſe the myſterie of finding the longitudes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theſe proiects depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth vpon the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netical poles, (for the finding out of which poles, I haue been enforced, to vſe the obſeruations of other men, wherein, if they haue failed, and I my ſelfe alſo haue done the like, in relying vpon them,) it may come to paſſe, that the longitudes cannot be by theſe my poles found out ſo exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as is to be wiſhed for, before ſuch time as the places of the ſaid poles be firſt, yet more truelie, found. Therefore if it ſhall happen to appeare, that the places of the ſaid poles, by me found out, be yet defectiue (which defect neuertheleſſe I am well aſſured will bee very little); I haue deuiſed a way,</p>
            <p n="24">24 How any man hauing ſome knowledge and practiſe in the Mathematicals, may by his owne obſeruations exactly find out the true longitude and latitude of the ſaid poles, (farre eaſier and with greater ſpeed then I haue done, or could doe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I had found the ſame another way,) and may alſo fit the ſame moſt commodiouſly, vnto the Art of Nauigation, and it vnto them as I haue done.</p>
            <p n="25">25 How (beſides this Globe and Chard) all other the inſtruments commonlie vſed in the Art of Nauigation, as the Compaſſe, the Aſtrolabe, the Quadrant, the Croſſe-ſtaffe, &amp; the Trauers boord, may be excellentlie well amended and perfected.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:9997:13"/>
            <p n="26">26 And beſides theſe mentioned premiſes, many other propoſitions and concluſions do occurre in this my Complement, both ſtrange and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; of which in this place I may not ſpeake.</p>
            <p>The other part of theſe my Newes compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth amongſt diuers other, theſe things fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The great Empire of <hi>Cataia,</hi> where it lieth, and the great riches of the ſame.</item>
               <item>2 The way by land from the confines of the <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian</hi> ſea, vnto the ſame.</item>
               <item>3 A new Geographicall deſcription of the <hi>Caſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> ſea, and of the Eaſterne and Northerne <hi>Tarta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> and of the Empire of <hi>Cataia,</hi> as it now lieth, far differing from the vſuall deſcriptions now extant amongſt vs, with the longitudes and latitudes of <hi>Cambalu,</hi> and <hi>Quinſay,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>4 That the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Empire vnder the great <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merlane,</hi> far ſurpaſſed in greatneſſe any of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires that euer haue been, or be, or are likely to be in ages to come.</item>
               <item>5 That there is greater hope then euer was here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, of a free and ſafe paſſage by ſea, Northerly from <hi>Europe</hi> to <hi>Cataia.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6 That I haue added the longitude of 50. or 60. degrees of good diſcouerie, vnto the alreadie
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:9997:13"/>knowne longitude, comprehended betweene the Weſterne coaſt of <hi>America,</hi> vnder the latitude of 67. degrees, on the one ſide, and the <hi>Vaygatz,</hi> or Ile <hi>Van Oranges,</hi> vpon the North of <hi>Noua Zemla,</hi> on the otherſide; but how and where the ſame is added, ſhall be ſaid elſewhere. And if two ſeuerall obſeruations, made by two ſeuerall Nauigators, of as great knowledge and iudgement in their Art and facultie, as any other of our age, had bin true; (as in all likelihood they ſeemed to me to be, and will ſo ſeeme alſo to other men, vntill they be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued) I might with the ſafety of my credit, haue affirmed, that I had fully diſcouered that paſſage.</item>
               <item>7 That the reſidue of that paſſage yet vndiſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, is leſſe by much, then it hath been thought to be.</item>
               <item>8 The ſtraits of <hi>Anian</hi> where they be; and of what largeneſſe.</item>
               <item>9 The fitteſt and moſt commodious way to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, for the diſcouery of the ſaid paſſage.</item>
               <item>10 That there is no doubt, but our nation may be entertained into a very rich trade of Merchandize, with the <hi>Cataians,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe be ſome part of theſe my Newes, ſo long hidden from the world, and ſo greatly deſired of our nation, but with little hope: for the reuealing whereof, (as I truſt) it hath pleaſed our moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious God, to make me (his moſt vnworthy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant)
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:9997:14"/>his inſtrument. And theſe benefits will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue thereof, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1 That the Art of Nauigation may in ſhort time, be brought vnto the higheſt perfection, ſo,</item>
               <item>2 That not only the feare conceiued in the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſea, printed at <hi>London, anno</hi> 1606. pag. 73. that they are likely to periſh, which happen to fall vnder the North-pole of the world, (and by like reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder the pole magneticall,) vnleſſe they be holpen by a clock, made and rectified before hand for that purpoſe; is cleerely taken away, and remoued. But alſo,</item>
               <item>3 That our Voyages and Diſcoueries, may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with more certaintie and readines, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with greater gaine, and with leſſe loſſe of liues and goods, then vſually hath been.</item>
               <item>4 That the Art of Nauigation requireth profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of greater skill and practiſe in the Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticals, then are now commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly to be found among them; in which notwithſtanding they may eaſily, and in ſhort time, attaine a good ſufficiencie for their profeſſion.</item>
               <item>5 That the diſcouerie of <hi>Cataia</hi> by any ſuppoſed Northerne Paſſage, further then hath bin alreadie diſcouered, cannot be ſafely and commodiouſly attempted, much leſſe performed, without the knowledge of this my Complement, and Naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gators
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:9997:14"/>of very good skill and practiſe in the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematiques.</item>
               <item>6 That this Complement taketh nothing away from the ordinary practiſe of Nauigation, nor al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth any thing in the ſame, ſaue only it addeth a Globe of a new deſcription, and a Map or two, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter M. <hi>Wrights</hi> mentioned Proiection, rectified, and one other ſea Map or two, of other Proiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; &amp; ſome other few Inſtruments, with the vſes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In the reſidue, men are left to their own or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie proceedings, although they may amend, or alter all, if they pleaſe, which verily is requiſite.</item>
               <item>7 That diuers opinions and doctrines of diuers learned men (whom for honors ſake I will not heere name) are hereby cleared, or confuted.</item>
               <item>8 That the worlds general Geographie may bee hereby very much amended, &amp; may in ſhort time be brought to the higheſt degree of perfection: ſo that the ſtudious of that Art, and of the Apode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miques of the ancient, meane, and moderne ages, may receiue therby great light and contentment.</item>
               <item>9 The benefits of planting the Goſpell amongſt thoſe <hi>Ethnique</hi> and Idolatrous nations of <hi>Cataia,</hi> and others by the way; the ſetting of our people aworke, the increaſe of Nauigators and men of ſeruice for other employments, the bringing in of great Treaſures into this Land, the turning of the trade of the Eſterne world, which the great
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:9997:15"/>
                  <hi>Turke</hi> on the one ſide, and the <hi>Spaniard</hi> and <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugale</hi> on the other ſide, haue now gotten almoſt all into their owne hands, beſides many other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentary benefits, I leaue to your wiſdomes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Gods mercy, in reuealing this Complement vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, I for my part, account a bleſſing ſo rare and precious, (not ſo much for the ſtrangenes and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie therof, as for the generall and continuall vſe and benefit thereof vnto mankind,) that if <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimedes</hi> in his daies had gotten it, he would haue runne once againe out of his bathing tubbe, with his ioyful crie, I haue found, I haue found. If <hi>Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Mileſius</hi> had attained it, he would haue offered one oxe for a ſacrifice of thankfulneſſe, as he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to haue done, for the finding out of the 2.3.4.5. Propoſ. of the fourth booke of <hi>Euclid.</hi> If <hi>Pythagoras</hi> had found it, he would haue offered an <hi>Hecatomben,</hi> or a ſacrifice of an hundred oxen, as it is ſaid he did, for the finding of the 47. and 48. Propoſ. of the firſt book of <hi>Euclid.</hi> How can I then, (far inferiour vnto the meaneſt of them in natures endowments, and humane learning,) chuſe (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I ſhould proue moſt vnthankfull vnto God,) but offer vnto his Maieſtie an <hi>Hecatomben</hi> of the calues of my lips, and ſay with the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> Pſal. 34.1. <hi>Benedicam Dominum in omni tempore, ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per laus eius in ore meo:</hi> and Pſal. 71.19. <hi>Benedictum nomen Maiestatis ſuae in aeternum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſith our good God hath beſtowed his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vpon me, not for mine owne ſake alone, but alſo for the benefit of his Church; fitting it is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:9997:15"/>that I ſhould employ the ſame vnto that end. I am willing in his name, and in his feare to do it, and to impart the firſt fruits thereof vnto you, for the honor and benefit of the Kings Maieſtie, and his Subiects of this his Imperiall Monarchie of Great <hi>Britaine,</hi> for whom it hath been long time reſerued. <hi>Engl. Voiag. vol.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 144.</p>
            <p>And to this end I offer and tender vnto you, and euery one of you, my ſelfe and my ſeruice, vpon meete and reaſonable conditions; ſo that if you miſſe thereof, the fault ſhall be your owne, and not mine.</p>
            <p>And this I proteſt vnto you, in holines and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie, that I verily beleeue, that if you miſſe of the ſame at my hands, being now growen into yeeres and haſtening vnto my graue, that neither this age preſent, nor ages to come, are likely to haue the ſame. For as by conference with other men, I haue gotten nothing that hath furthered me in theſe my trauels; but haue relied my ſelfe wholly vpon mine owne collections, gathered out of ſuch few printed books, as I could get: for hiſtories and the reports of Trauellers, are the treaſurie of theſe My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries; as ſaith <hi>Ptol.</hi> in his <hi>Geogr. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2. (ſauing that the Worſhipfull <hi>Iohn Wood,</hi> Doctor of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and Parſon of S. <hi>Dionis Backchurch</hi> in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> a Gentleman exceeding willing to further our Countries good, and my very kind friend, whom I once entreated to procure me, from his acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that haue trauelled to the Eaſt <hi>Indies,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, ſome certaine obſeruations, (which yet hitherto he could not do,) hath imparted vnto
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:9997:16"/>me, certaine books of the Eaſt <hi>Indies,</hi> out of which I haue gotten ſome light, touching the ſituation of thoſe Eaſterne countries.) So likewiſe haue I not communicated vnto any man, any thing of theſe my Concluſions, which may giue light for the finding out of this my Complement, or any Northerne Paſſage vnto our deſired <hi>Cataia:</hi> this Epiſtle only excepted. And further I am aſſured, that this ſecret lieth ſo incloſed and locked vp in the manifold darke retraits of natures Cabbinet, that it is plainly impoſſible for any wit of man, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer at any time to bring the ſame to light, vnleſſe it ſhall pleaſe the only wiſe and all-ſeeing God, to bleſſe him extraordinarily for the ſame. Let the Aſſayes and worthie attempts, of many excellent and greatlearned men, ſome dead, ſome liuing, all failing of their end and purpoſe herein, be cleare and ſufficient teſtimonies vnto you of the truth hereof.</p>
            <p>I aſſure my ſelfe that theſe ſtrange Newes, and ſuch confidence in profeſſing of the ſame, wil pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce diuers effects in the harts and in the mouthes of many that ſhal reade or heare the ſame; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome few whereof, I addreſſe the reſidue of this my Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>Some ſicke of a Proſopoleptique affection, which in this age raigneth far and neere, will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently bee drawen (without any reſpect of the worke it ſelfe) into admiration of the Author, as a man rarely qualified, and graced with extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie ornaments of learning, &amp;c. and following their opinions of ſuppoſed ſingularitie, will enter
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:9997:16"/>into a ſtrict <hi>inquirendum,</hi> who is this? who may this bee? Theſe ſhall receiue anſwere from my night neighbour the <hi>Owle,</hi> from the tree of her watch, in this Pöem.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Si rogites quis ſit? <hi>Lintonum</hi> noſce virum quem</l>
               <l>Quaeris: Syluanum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> patrem, Satyroſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> minaces,</l>
               <l>Noſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> inter nemori gentem, tristeſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Chimaeras,</l>
               <l>Lucubrat; at muſis alienus &amp; exul amicis,</l>
               <l>Indigus Authorum, rerum cui deficit vſus.</l>
               <l>Statgenio charus, ſuffultus numine Diûum,</l>
               <l>Ille voluptatis gremio, ambitionis iniqua</l>
               <l>Fastu posthabitis, iustâ &amp; de rebus habendis</l>
               <l>Curâ: fastidium Noctis, rigidoſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> labores</l>
               <l>Excutiens, animo praeclara molimina voluens,</l>
               <l>Impiger effecit proauis non cognita veſtris,</l>
               <l>In patrios vſus Anglorum gentis honorem.</l>
               <l>Atque amor in patriam tantos ſtimulauit in auſus.</l>
               <l>Eſt igitur pietatis opus.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>Some (forgetting that God for the greater ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of his owne glorie, and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of other, doth oftentimes by meane and weake inſtruments bring to paſſe his great and maruellous works) will for the meaneneſſe of the Author diſable the worke, and either of contempt demand with the Poet:</p>
            <q>Quid feret hic dignum tanto promiſſor hiatu?</q>
            <p>Or elſe of malice depraue it, as the Athenians did the doctrine of the bleſſed Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Act. 17.18.</p>
            <q>Nouorum Daemoniorum videtur eſſe annunciator.</q>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:9997:17"/>
            <p>Thus was that worthie <hi>Columbus</hi> vſed whileſt he tendred the diſcouerie of the Weſt Indies (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had yet diſcouered the ſame) as you may reade in our Engliſh voiag. vol. 3. pag. 167. In which notwithſtanding hee fullie ſatiſfied the world. And ſo haue I, in times paſt, been vſed. For a learned Gentleman demanding of me in the preſence of diuers other, whether I thought it poſſible to find out the longitudes of places by ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall obſeruation, without the helpe of any Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clips? And I plainely anſwering, that I thought it poſſible, tooke hereupon occaſion, to reprooue openly, the vanity of them that will raſhlie affirme things meerely impoſſible, ſuch as he ſaid he took that to be, by the generall confeſſion of all learned men, &amp;c. And I now for my part, deſirous to cleere my ſelfe from that imputation, and to giue you ſome hope of the certentie of this my promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Complement, will heare deliuer ſome reaſon, why I thinke ſo, by the demonſtration of this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing problem.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Problem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of two places giuen, either vnder the equino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiall, or vnder any one parallel of the world, or not much different; of which two places, the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude of one is knowne; and the longitude of the other is not knowne: by celeſtiall obſeruation, to be made (in conuenient time, and in that place of the twaine, whoſe longitude is not knowne) of the Moones viſible acceſſe, vnto the meridian of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:9997:17"/>the ſame place; to find out the difference of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude betweene the ſaid two giuen places, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the longitude of the other place, at all ſuch times, without reſpect of any ecclips.</p>
            <p>For the finding of theſe premiſes, you muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that the Moone being caried about the earth, by the force of the <hi>primum mobile,</hi> from the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian of any place, paſſeth within the ſpace of 24. houres and ſame 48. minuts of an houre, little more or leſſe, ouer all the meridians of the world, (which are the whole longitude of 360. degrees) before ſhe be brought againe vnto the meridian of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame place, during which time of 24. houres, and 48. minuts <hi>quaſi,</hi> ſhe proceedeth forwards in her owne proper motion <hi>ſecundùm ſucceſſum ſignorum:</hi> onely the ſaid 48. minuts <hi>quaſi:</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſhe ſhould be brought vnto the ſame me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian againe, in the ſpace of 24. houres, as the Sun is. And hereby it is manifeſt that the greateſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of longitude betweene any two places, is alwaies compriſed within 48. minuts <hi>quaſi,</hi> of the Moones progreſſe in her proper motion: the diur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reuolation of 24. houres being alwaies whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reiected.</p>
            <p>This being ſo, I ſay, that only by theſe 48. mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts <hi>quaſi,</hi> and a celeſtiall obſeruation to be made, may be found, both the difference of longitude betweene the two giuen places, and alſo the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude of that other place, whoſe longitude is not knowne.</p>
            <p>For the minutes of time which the Moone ſpendeth in her owne proper courſe, during the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:9997:18"/>time that ſhe is carried by the violence of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, from the meridian of any one place, vntill ſhe be brought vnto the ſame meridian againe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing giuen: together with the minuts of time which the Moone in her owne proper motion loſt, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt ſhe was carried from the meridian of the one place, vnto the meridian of the other place: the former part of the problem, <hi>viz.</hi> the difference of longitude betweene the ſaid two places may bee found. <hi>Fiat enim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the whole number of minutes wherein the Moone proceedeth in her proper motion, during the time that ſhe is caried, from the meridian of that giuen place, whoſe longitude is knowne, vntil ſhe be brought thither againe, (which whole num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of minutes is alwaies 48. <hi>quaſi;</hi>) is in propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vnto the whole longitude of 360. degrees; ſo is the number of the minutes, wherein the Moone proceedeth in her proper motion, whiles ſhe is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried from the meridian of either of the giuen pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, (rightly applied,) to the meridian of the other place; vnto the difference of longitude betweene the ſaid two giuen places.</p>
            <p>The moſt conuenient time for obſeruation is in a faire calme ſtarrie night, and eſpecially when the Moone ſhall be in, or neere either of the Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piques.</p>
            <p>The manner of proceeding in this worke is thus.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, in the place of obſeruation, find the true meridian line preciſely, and obſerue the Moone, vntill you ſee her centre directly in the ſame meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:9997:18"/>And at that very moment of time, (by the height of ſome fixed ſtarre, taken, or otherwiſe) find out the true houre and minute of the night.</item>
               <item>Secondly, by moſt exact tables made, or to bee made, deliuering the true houre and minute wherein the Moone in her apparent motion commeth euery day to the meridian of that giuen place, whoſe longitude is knowne. Find out the number of minutes of time which the Moone ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, whileſt ſhe was carried from the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian of that giuen place, vntill ſhe come thither againe. And this number is alwaies the firſt in the rule of proportion; as the whole longitude of 360. degrees is alwaies the ſecond.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, by the ſame tables ſeeke out the houre and minute of time, wherein the moone was laſt, or ſhall be next, (reſpecting the time of your ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation) in the meridian of that place whoſe longitude is knowne, being alſo the place for which the tables are or ſhould be compoſed.</item>
               <item>Fourthly, compare the houre and minutes of time found by obſeruation, and the houre and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute of time found by the tables, and ſo ſhall you haue the difference of time; which is alwaies the third number in the rule of proportion; hauing therefore your three numbers, proceed according to the nature of the worke, and your quotient ſhall be the difference of longitude betweene the two giuen places, which was the thing firſt to bee found.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The latter part of the problem may thus bee found.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:9997:19"/>
            <p>This difference being found, muſt either be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto the longitude of the place giuen, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted from the ſame, or elſe be ſubtracted from the whole longitude, as the worke requireth. And ſo alſo ſhall be had the longitude of the ſecond place, where the obſeruation was made; which was ſecondlie to be found out.</p>
            <p>Example 1. The difference of longitude be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>London</hi> and the <hi>grand Bay</hi> in <hi>Newfound</hi> land, ſuppoſed to bee in the ſame latitude, is thus found. Vpon the 13. day of Februarie, 1607. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the old ſtile, the Moone (ſuppoſe) was found in her apparent motion to be in the Meridian of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> at 11. of the clocke at night, by the tables of her daily approch to that meridian, and that ſhee ſhould be there againe the next night, at 11. of the clocke and 48. minuts: The verie ſame night by obſeruation made at the ſaid <hi>grand Bay,</hi> the Moone was ſeene in the meridian there, at 10. of the clocke at night and 50. minuts; ſo that from the time, that ſhe had been in the Meridian of <hi>London,</hi> vnto the time that ſhe came vnto the Meridian of the <hi>grand Bay,</hi> ſhe had proceeded forwards in her owne proper motion 9. minuts of time. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the rule of proportion; If 48. minuts of time giue 360. degrees of longitude; what ſhall 9. minuts of time giue? It is anſwered in the quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, gr. 67. m 30. the degrees of the difference of longitude betweene the ſaid two places; which was firſt to be found.</p>
            <p>If from this number you ſubtract the longitude of <hi>London</hi> gr. 23. m. 30. the remainder is gr. 44.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:9997:19"/>m.o. ſubduct them from 360. the whole longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and the remander will be 316. degrees; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the longitude of the <hi>grand Bay,</hi> which was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly to be found out.</p>
            <p>Example 2. Suppoſe that the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Moſcowe</hi> bee in the ſame parallel. Now the difference of longitude betweene them, is thus found out. Vpon the 22. day of December, after the old ſtile, <hi>anno.</hi> 1607. the Moone in her appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent motion was found by tables in the Meridian of <hi>London</hi> at 2. of the clocke after midnight. And the minuts of her progreſſe in that whole reuolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of longitudes were 48. Alſo at <hi>Moskowe</hi> that very ſame night ſhe was ſeene, by obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there, at 1. of the clocke, and 52. minuts after midnight; ſo that ſhe was yet to proceed in her owne proper motion 8. minutes of time, before ſhe ſhould come againe to the Meridian of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi> Therefore if 48. minuts of time giue 360. degrees of longitude, what ſhall 8. minutes giue? It is anſwered, 60. which is the difference of lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude betweene the ſaid Cities, the thing firſt to be found. This done, adde theſe 60. degrees vnto the longitude of <hi>London, viz.</hi> gr. 23. m. 30. the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct will be gr. 83. m. 30. the longitude of <hi>Moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kowe;</hi> which was ſecondlie to be found.</p>
            <p>There is no doubt but the longituds may bee found this way, for,</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, the Meridian line may preciſely bee had by obſeruation. And</item>
               <item>ſecondly, ſo may the houre and minute of time, the houre being 15. degrees of a great circle, and the minute of an houre of 15.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:9997:20"/>minutes of a degree. And yet the eleuations of the pole and altitudes of the celeſtiall lights, are found out euen vnto one of thoſe minuts of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and leſſe. And therefore one minute of time, (being 15. of them) may alſo be found. For in an inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the ſemidiameter of whoſe Equinocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all circle ſhall be. 6. foote, one minute of time ſhall be almoſt one third of an inch. And the ſemidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter being three foote, one minute of time ſhall be one ſixth part of an inch almoſt.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, tables alſo may bee had deliuering ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly the houre and minute, wherein the Moone in her apparent motion, commeth euery day to the Meridian of that place, for which the tables be, or are to be made; for indeede all theſe three things haue in former times been had, otherwiſe there could haue been at this day no theoriques of the planets or tables of the celeſtiall motions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs.</item>
            </list>
            <p>This way alſo of finding the longitude is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent good, and may come often into practiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the proportion of 48. minuts of time or thereabouts (which make ſome 12. degrees and 30. minuts <hi>quaſi,</hi> of a great circle) is ſufficientlie great to the whole longitude of 360. degrees. For if 48. minuts of time, giue 360. degrees of longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, then ſhall 24. giue 180. degrees, and 12. ſhall giue 90. degrees, and 6. ſhall giue 45. degrees. and 3. ſhall giue 21. degrees and an halfe. And 1. minute ſhall giue 7. degrees and an halfe, &amp;c. And the difference of longitude in any one parallel that ſhall bee leſſe then 7. degrees and an halfe,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:9997:20"/>may otherwiſe bee found out, theſe former being firſt had.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, it is certaine that in places of diuers latituds, yea euen in one and the ſame Meridian, (and therefore much more in diuers) the Moones parallaxes in longitude, doe not happen in one and the ſame moment of time, neither are of one and the ſame magnitude, but in ſome places they happen ſooner, in ſome places later. In ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they be greater, and in ſome places they be leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, the reconciling of which differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, eſpeciallie in places of diuers Meridians, and latitudes, bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth much combrance and difficultie euen to the skilfull Mathemat. in ſeeking the longitudes without ecclipſes. But by this taking of two pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces vnder the Equinoctial or vnder the ſame paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel, all ſenſible difference that may happen in 12. houres and an halfe, either in the time, or in the magnitudes of the parallaxes, with all incombran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and impediments following the ſame, are ſufficiently auoided. Whereby it is euident, that at all times (fit for obſeruation) whenſoeuer the Moone may beſeene in the meridian of the place of obſeruation, (which doubtleſſe is verie often, ſo that a ſhip need not ſtay long in any port for the ſame) ſo often the longitude of that place may be found, eſpecially if the giuen places haue great difference of longitude.</p>
            <p>But in this worke great regard muſt be had, that the inſtruments which are vſed for the ſame, bee apt and large, and verie good, and with great dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and exactnes managed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9997:21"/>
            <p>And if the longitude of ſome few places, were either thus, or rather by Ecclipſes found, as of <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, Iapon, Macao, Bantam,</hi> or <hi>Malacca, Goa, Aden, Mozambique, Cape de bona Eſperanza, Cap. Verde, Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nambuco,</hi> the ſtraits of <hi>Magellan, Panama, California, Virginea, Cap. Raſo, Tercera, Bergen</hi> in <hi>Norway, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogro, Moſcua, Aſtracan,</hi> and <hi>Tripoli</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> &amp;c. which might eaſilie be done either by the Naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gators reſorting vnto them, or by other learned Chriſtians inhabiting there, I beleeue that the worlds Geographie, and the Art of Nauigation, would thereby be much amended.</p>
            <p>There is yet another way to find ſometimes the longitude of ſuch places as are vnder either of the Tropiques, or betweene them, as certainly as by Ecclipſes, <hi>viz.</hi> In the very moment of time, when the Moone ſhall be ſeene in the Zenith, (for then ſhe hath in the place of obſeruation, no parallax of longitude) or very neere vnto the Zenith, (and the better) ſhe being neere vnto either of the Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piques, and in the meridian) find out by one ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, the houre and minute of time, and by another obſeruation at the ſame moment, find (by the ſtaffe) the diſtance between the Centre of the Moone, &amp; ſome notable fixed Star in, or neere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Eccliptique. Then ſecondly, gather by the magnitude of the Moons diurnal motion, <hi>ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſucceſſum ſignorum,</hi> (which you may find by the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemerides,</hi> for that day,) the houre and minute of time of her laſt, or next coniunction with the ſame fixed Starre. Thirdly, by the helpe of the ſame time of coniunction, collect alſo by ſupputation,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:9997:21"/>the houre and minute of time wherin the Moone ſhall be next, or was laſt, in the point of ☌, or ☍ or other aſpect with the Sunne, (all which ſerue for that place of obſeruation, wherin the Moone was ſeene in the Zenith.) And fourthly, compare this time of ☌. or ☍. or other aſpect ſo found, with the time of the ☌. or ☍. or other aſpect which you ſhall find in the <hi>Ephemerides</hi> for that day alſo, and belongeth vnto the Radical place of the ſaid <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merides,</hi> and the difference of thoſe two times in houres and minutes, will giue the difference of longitude, betweene the place where the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation is made, and the Radicall place of the <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merides,</hi> very ſufficiently.</p>
            <p>Thus, I hope, I haue ſhewed ſufficient reaſon, why I thinke the longitude may bee found, by celeſtiall obſeruation, without reſpect of any Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe. And therefore alſo haue cleered my ſelfe from the Gentlemans imputation in this behalfe, and withall giuen you ſome hope of the certaintie of this my promiſed Complement; wherein ſome things ſtand vpon the obſeruations, relations, and credible concurring teſtimonies of approued Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, and generally receiued opinions; and theſe be of ſufficient warrantize, vntill they be diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: And ſome things are from theſe former, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by Mathematicall Demonſtrations, which ſeldome faile. And therefore theſe humors of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudication may perceiue, that it is better, and more commendable, to forbeare (at leaſt for a time) to extenuate or depraue the reputations of men, for affirming the poſſibilitie of ſuch things, as they the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:9997:22"/>ſaid humors haue yet neuer ſeene, much leſſe exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined; then otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Some will maruell, and ſome will miſlike that I ſhould take this courſe for the publiſhing of theſe my Newes. To theſe I anſwere, that diuers reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s do neceſſarily require the ſame at my ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds.</p>
            <p>Firſt it is needfull that there ſhould bee ſome publique notice giuen thereof, whereby it may be publiquely knowne, as Innes haue their ſignes, and Tauerns their Iuies. It is an old ſaying and holden true:</p>
            <q>Scire tuum nihil est, niſi te ſcire, hoc ſciat alter.</q>
            <p>Secondly, I held it neceſſarie to be publiſhed at the firſt in this manner, to preuent the practiſes of many euill diſpoſed men, which vſe with all cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to impart vnto ſtrangers, they care not whom, (ſo they may gaine a few pence thereby,) yea and to tranſport into other cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries, whatſoeuer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth into their hands, euen the food and clothing of their poore neighbours, without remorſe or compaſſion: yea and the ſecrets of their countries eſtate, without reſpect; being thereby guiltie of no leſſe crime then prodition, if they do the ſame without the allowance of the ſupreme Magiſtrate. <hi>Mali ciues, mali homines,</hi> and like enough one day to heare,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Vendidit hic auro patriam, Dominum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> potentem</l>
               <l>Impoſuit, leges fixit pretio, atque refixit.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And ſo doubtleſſe will do with this my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, if it ſhall come into their power, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof, our neighbour nations ſhall know the vſe thereof, as ſoone as your ſelues, and wil no
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:9997:22"/>doubt (as much as in them lieth) preuent you of the honor and benefit thereof. Whereas my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is, that our nation may haue the firſt fruits of the ſame.</p>
            <p>And alſo I reſolued of this manner of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing hereof, to reſerue vnto my ſelfe, as the only Author of the ſaid Complement (next and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after God) the credit and eſtimation ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, if it ſhall happen to find any. For many there be, that will forget, not only to giue vnto others their due, but contrariwiſe, will ſubtract from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers their right; and not contented ſo, will arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate the ſame vnto themſelues, or deriue it vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Into which foule fault, I feare me, <hi>Iodocus Hondius,</hi> a man otherwiſe well deſeruing of Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphie, is likely one day to fall, ouer head and eares; hauing in times paſt, waded ſo far into that puddle; as appeareth, firſt, by the Inuectiue of M. <hi>Edward Wright,</hi> againſt him the ſaid <hi>Iodocus Hondius,</hi> publiſhed in the Preface of his booke of of errors of Nauigation, printed at <hi>London,</hi> 1599.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, by the great quarter Maps of the ſaid <hi>Iod. Hondius,</hi> printed at <hi>Amſterdam, anno</hi> 1602. in which Maps he hath tranſlated the diſcouerie of the <hi>Vaygatz,</hi> (made by our Engliſh, and firſt, by <hi>Stephen Burrowes, anno</hi> 1556. vnder the commiſſion of King <hi>Philip</hi> and Queene <hi>Marie,</hi> bearing that date. And againe the ſecond time, by <hi>Arthur Pet, anno Dom.</hi> 1583. vnder the commiſſion of Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of famous memorie, bearing that date. By which Diſcoueries, it might iuſtly haue been inſerted into their Maps, by the name of <hi>fretum
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:9997:23"/>Reg. Angliae,</hi> &amp;c.) from the Imperiall crowne of <hi>England,</hi> vnto the houſe of <hi>Naſtaw,</hi> intituling it, <hi>Fretum Naſſouicum;</hi> whereas, that otherwiſe truly noble houſe of <hi>Naſtow,</hi> neuer did any thing for the firſt diſcouering of the ſame. This fault is great, and doubtleſſe offenſiue vnto our whole nation, if it conſider thereof. I could wiſh him, in good friendſhip, to be better aduiſed hereafter, of falling into the like exceſſe.</p>
            <p>Leſſe by much is the ouerſight (in that kind,) committed by that learned <hi>Petrus Plantius,</hi> who in his generall Map publiſhed in <hi>London, anno Dom.</hi> 1595. &amp; vnder the Imperiall Armes of the crowne of <hi>England,</hi> neere vnto <hi>Quiuira</hi> vpon the We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne ſhore of <hi>America</hi> in his ſaid Mappe, hath left out <hi>Noua Albion,</hi> without making any mention of the ſame, ſmothering thereby as much as in him lay, firſt the renowme of that worthie Sir <hi>Francis Drake</hi> Knight, who firſt diſcouered the ſame, <hi>anno Dom.</hi> 1578. beſides whom, neuer any man hath ſailed further that way, for any thing that is pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely knowne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſecondly, empayring in that point, for his power, the memorie of that worthie action of our nation, and the extent of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall crowne of <hi>England,</hi> vnto whoſe right, the ſaid <hi>Drake</hi> tooke poſſeſſion of that countrie, as lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he might do, not finding there, the Banners, or Enſignes of any Chriſtian Prince, nor the ſaid country in the poſſeſſion or occupation of any Chriſtian people, as he the ſaid <hi>Plantius</hi> right wel knew.</p>
            <p>This omiſſion of his therefore, in this caſe, is
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:9997:23"/>worthie of blame; but yet he did not tranſport the ſame, by word, or by writing, vnto the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> or vnto any other Prince, or Potentate, as <hi>Iod. Hondius</hi> hath done the other.</p>
            <p>And of this kind of derogators, and arrogators, and tranſporting kind of men, there wanteth no ſtore at any time, in euery Common-wealth. Of which kind of men, I my poore ſelfe in mine own particular, haue in times paſt receiued wrong, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing any more to endure the like; or elſe with griefe, to reclaime my loſſes, by the way of chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge; as in old time did the Pöet <hi>Virgil,</hi> vpon the Court gates of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> his verſes, with theſe verſes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Hos ego verſiculo feci, tulit alter honores:</l>
               <l>Sic vos non vobis—</l>
               <l>Sic vos non vobis—</l>
            </q>
            <p>Further, becauſe theſe newes are generall, and doe concerne all the ſubiects of this Imperiall Crowne of great <hi>Britaine,</hi> I ſuppoſed that if I ſhould haue dedicated the ſame to any ſpecial per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, I ſhould thereby haue giuen iuſt offence vnto many vertuous minds, in cutting off from them al occaſion to helpe forward the finiſhing of this my concluded complement; and therefore I haue reaſon to publiſh theſe my Concluſions after this faſhion.</p>
            <p>Laſtlie, ſeeing it is not likelie (for many reaſons as my caſe now ſtandeth) that I ſhall be able, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring my life, to make vp this my complement into a volume for record, I thought it beſt in this ſort to make it known, to the end that you, for your parts,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:9997:24"/>might without any trauell or expenſes, ſufficiently conſider of the thing it ſelfe, and alſo of the vſe and benefit thereof, and ſo take occaſion to entertaine, or reiect the ſame. And that I, for my part, might diſcharge my conſcience towards God in thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and towards his Church, eſpecially my Countrie, and your ſelues, in loue and ſeruice.</p>
            <p>Thus therefore hauing finiſhed my Nauigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and being returned from <hi>Cataia,</hi> and arriued at home, I will there reſt for this time, and (omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all other narrations, and exhortations) Ieaue you to the Apoſtles rule, Rom. 14.5. <hi>Vnuſquiſque abundet ſuo ſenſu:</hi> Euery one of you (in this behalfe) to doe ſo, as his owne wiſdome ſhall thinke it beſt. And ſo with my dutie vnto you, and euerie one of you reſpectiuely performed, I bid you heartily <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my ſtudie in <hi>Worth</hi> 
                  <date>this 24. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uemb. 1608.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Yours <hi>Antho. Linton.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="envoy">
            <head>The Authors farewel to his Epiſtle.</head>
            <q>
               <l>Vade liber tenuis, dignos Exquire patronos,</l>
               <l>Nec pudeat titulos fronte tuliſſe meos.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="Britain_to_author">
            <head>Britannia magna ad Authorem: Progeniem ſuam.</head>
            <l>Christi Euangelium populo impartire palanti,</l>
            <l>Gratum opus, &amp; quo nil maius dicatur; at extrà</l>
            <l>Quid Lintone paras? magnarum nuncia rerum?</l>
            <l>Res fac perficias, &amp; eris mihi gratus Alumnus.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
